<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Dopamine on Shawn&#39;s Note</title>
        <link>http://shawn1251.github.io/tags/dopamine/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Dopamine on Shawn&#39;s Note</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://shawn1251.github.io/tags/dopamine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Addiction Recovery</title>
        <link>http://shawn1251.github.io/post/addiction-recovery/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://shawn1251.github.io/post/addiction-recovery/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This note is from the video &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LbbyLeR1ZRk&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;心河擺渡-成瘾始于痛苦，戒瘾终于平衡！深度解读多巴胺，用身体内稳态戒瘾&lt;/a&gt; The video contains insights from the author as well as his analysis of Anna Lembke&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Drug-Dealer-MD-Doctors-Patients/dp/1421421402&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Drug Dealer, MD: How Doctors Were Duped, Patients Got Hooked, and Why It’s So Hard to Stop.&lt;/a&gt; The content is very useful, and I made notes to remind myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;underlying-principles&#34;&gt;Underlying Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reason behind addiction is the increase in dopamine.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chocolate increases it by 55%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicotine raises it by 150%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amphetamine boosts it by 1000%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main role of dopamine is not to make us feel happy after receiving a reward but to drive people to seek rewards.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, when you see chocolate, dopamine activates the brain&amp;rsquo;s reward circuit, making you feel pleasure even before having it and prompting you to eat it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The regions in the brain responsible for pleasure and pain overlap.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pleasure and pain have self-regulating functions. When you&amp;rsquo;re currently experiencing pleasure, the brain will generate enough pain on the other side to balance it out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward Prediction Error
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Due to neural adaptation, the actual reward must exceed expectations to have a positive dopamine effect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In severe addiction, the threshold for feeling pleasure increases, resulting in a lack of enjoyment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;utilizing-the-dopamine-mechanism&#34;&gt;Utilizing the Dopamine Mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to clinical experience, recreating the brain&amp;rsquo;s reward circuit takes at least a month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using pain to treat pain
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The brain uses pain to balance out pleasure and vice versa.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to research, dopamine levels in the blood plasma increase by 250% when people immerse themselves in cold water, and this effect lasts longer than the immersion time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise is the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical separation
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completely separate from the addictive substance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radical honesty
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The prefrontal cortex is responsible for rational decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the dopamine reward circuit is active, lying inhibits the prefrontal cortex&amp;rsquo;s function, releasing the restraint on the reward circuit, leading the brain to believe it&amp;rsquo;s not addicted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An essential part of addiction recovery is rebuilding the relationship between the prefrontal cortex and the dopamine circuit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strengthen the prefrontal cortex by &amp;ldquo;telling the truth&amp;rdquo; and enhance self-control.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During addiction, engage in self-talk or announce your addiction to people around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
